Guide to the Philip Kapleau papers, 1952-2009 and undated RL.11661
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Philip Kapleau papers
1952-2009 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Kapleau, Philip, 1912-2004
RL.11661
24 Linear Feet
Zen Buddhist teacher and author of "The Three Pillars of Zen." Born in New Haven, Connecticut, Kapleau was a chief court reporter for the Nuremberg Trials and also covered the Tokyo War Crimes Trials. While in Japan for the trials, he met and was influenced by D.T. Suzuki and other Zen practitioners, which led him to become a serious student of Zen in Japan. Eventually, he returned to the United States and founded the Rochester Zen Center (New York) in 1966. Most of the papers relate to Kapleau's role as a Zen teacher, to his writings, and to personal concerns such as his health and Parkinson's disease. Some of Kapleau's notes are written in shorthand, and there are some materials in Japanese. The recorded teishos (dharma talks) were mainly recorded during sesshin (retreats) and span 30 years. According to the tape labels, there are various speakers including Kapleau, Toni Packer, and Bodhin Kjolhede (all of whom led the Rochester Zen Center at different times).
Arrangement
Arranged into three series: Correspondence, Subject Files, and Recorded Teishos (Dharma talks). Original file names were maintained when possible.
Biographical / Historical
Zen Buddhist teacher and author of several books, including "The Three Pillars of Zen." Born in New Haven, Connecticut, Kapleau was a chief court reporter for the Nuremberg Trials, and he also covered the Tokyo War Crimes Trials. While in Japan for the trials, he met and was influenced by D.T. Suzuki and other Zen practitioners. He returned to the United States and attended classes taught by D.T. Suzuki at Columbia University. He then decided to go back to Japan and to become a serious student of Zen. He stayed in Japan for 13 years and studied with Zen Master Hakuun Yasutani and others. Eventually, he returned to the United States and founded the Rochester Zen Center (New York) in 1966. He is credited with spreading Zen Buddhism to Westerners through his writings and teachings.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Philip Kapleau Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2018 and 2019.
Collection Overview
Papers related to Kapleau's role as a Zen teacher, to his writings, and to his personal concerns such as his health and Parkinson's disease. He corresponded with students and Zen practitioners all over the world and kept copies of his responses. There are a few notable letters from the 1950s, one from D.T. Suzuki and one from Hakuun Yasutani (written to Kapleau's sister Jean Kapleau). Many of the letters are from people who learned about Kapleau by reading his book, "The Three Pillars of Zen." Other letters pertain to the Rochester Zen Center (New York) and many other Zen centers. The subject files contain articles (many that are written by others), clippings, newsletters, and notes related to politics, animal rights, religion, environmentalism, Zen workshops, psychotherapy, travel, and health and diet. Some of Kapleau's notes are written in shorthand and there are some materials in Japanese. The recorded teishos (dharma talks) were mainly recorded during sesshin (retreats). According to the tape labels, there are various speakers including Kapleau, Toni Packer, and Bodhin Kjolhede (all of whom led the Rochester Zen Center at different times).
Conditions Governing Access
Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Contact Research Services in advance to request the production of listening or viewing copies.
Rochester (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century.; Zen Buddhism -- Japan -- 20th century.; Zen Buddhism -- North America -- 20th century.; Packer, Toni, 1927-; Kjolhede, Bodhin, 1948-; Yasutani, Hakuun, 1885-1973; Suzuki, Daisetz Teitaro; Rochester Zen Center
- Correspondence, 1954-2009 and undated; 1
  - A, 1977-1999; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Abe, Masao, 1977-1980 (Box 1)
  - Aitken, Robert, 1973-1999; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Animals and Buddhism articles, 1983-1986 (Box 1)
  - Argentina, 1982-1986 (Box 1)
  - Australia, 1980-1988 (Box 1)
  - B, 1963-2004; 8 folders (Box 1)
  - Baker, Randy, 1993-1995 (Box 1)
  - Beacon Press, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Bedard, Jim, 1996-1999 (Box 1)
  - Bishop, Mitra, 1987-2002; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Blackman, Sushila, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Blofield, John, 1965-1986 (Box 15)
  - Brazil, 1980-1984 (Box 15)
  - Buddhists Concerned for Animals, 1982-1985 (Box 1)
  - Buddhist Peace Fellowship, 1995 (Box 1)
  - C, 1971-2002; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Canada, 1989-1994 (Box 1)
  - Carlson, Chet and Dorris, 1965-1967; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Ch'an Center: Ven. Sheng-yen, 1984-1985 (Box 1)
  - Chapin Mill Fundraising, 1996-2002 (Box 1)
  - Chapin, Ralph and Sanna, 1967-1979 (Box 1)
  - Chapin, Ralph, 1980-1987 (Box 1)
  - Chicago Zen Center, 1984-2000 (Box 1)
  - Chile, 1984 (Box 1)
  - China, 1981-1994 (Box 1)
  - To Cherish All Life, 1981-1998 (Box 1)
  - To Cherish All Life Chinese edition, 1983-1999 (Box 1)
  - Colombia, 1979-1985 (Box 1)
  - Congressmen, 1993-1994 (Box 1)
  - Costa Rica, 1982-1986 (Box 15)
  - Costa Rica, 1995-1996 (Box 1)
  - Curtiss, Kshantin, 1993-1995 (Box 1)
  - Czechoslovakia, 1990 (Box 1)
  - D, 1980-2003; 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Death and Dying, 1972-1974 (Box 2)
  - Death and Dying Book, 1986-1988 (Box 2)
  - Democrat and Chronicle, 1970-1983 (Box 2)
  - Denver Zen Center, 1983-2003; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Doubleday, 1975-1996; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Doubleday, Trace Murphy, 1994-1995 (Box 2)
  - E, 1981-2001; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Eisendrath, Polly and Ed Epstein, 1993-2000; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Embler, Ken, 1993-2000 (Box 2)
  - England, 1980-1994; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Ecuador, 1980 (Box 15)
  - F, 1980-2003; 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Faust, George, 1992-2001; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - France, 1983-1992; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Frank, Casey, 1989-2004; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Friends of the Western Buddhist Order Ven. Sangharakshita, 1973-1986 (Box 2)
  - Frey, Edward, 1994 (Box 2)
  - G, 1989-1997 (Box 2)
  - G, 1980-2003; 5 folders (Box 3)
  - Germany, 1980-1995; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Granat, Bob and Carolyn, 1992-1999 (Box 3)
  - Gratwick, Harriet, 1991-1998 (Box 3)
  - Greulich, Peter, 1994-2001 (Box 3)
  - H, 1980-2003; 4 folders (Box 3)
  - H, 1984-1988 (Box 15)
  - Hanh, Thich Nhat, 1973-1974 (Box 3)
  - Hungary, 1974 (Box 3)
  - I, 1982-2001 (Box 3)
  - India, 1968-1984 (Box 15)
  - Institute for Advanced Studies of World Religions, 1983-1985 (Box 3)
  - Israel, 1982-1987 (Box 3)
  - Italy, 1971-1986 (Box 3)
  - J, 1980-2001; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Jamaica, 1974-1976 (Box 3)
  - Japan, 1966-1992; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Jones, Ken, 1980-1986 (Box 3)
  - K, 1967-2004; 5 folders (Box 3)
  - Kapleau, Maitreyi (deLancey), 1987-2000 (Box 3)
  - Kapleau and Mauterer-Levy Wedding Invitation, undated (Box 15)
  - Kapleau, Sudarshana, 1992-2003; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Korea, 1989 (Box 3)
  - Kraft, Ken, 1978-2002; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Kraft, Ken Book on the Three Pillars, 1998-1999 (Box 3)
  - Kramer, Charlotte and Lee, 1992-1997 (Box 3)
  - L, 1968-1988; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - L, 1988-2002; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Lang, Richard, 1989-1992 (Box 4)
  - Langer, Stephen, Dr., 1992-1993 (Box 4)
  - Leisure-Automation Age, 1966-1969 (Box 4)
  - Lesser, Elizabeth (Omega), 1995 (Box 4)
  - Letter to people who inquire about practicing Zen in Japan, 1983 (Box 4)
  - Letters to be read at Teishos, 1966-1995; 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Life Center for Attitudinal Healing, 1987 (Box 4)
  - Lincoln, Abe, 1863 (Box 4)
  - Literary Agents, 1975-1995 (Box 4)
  - Lithuania, 1990-1992 (Box 4)
  - Lovegren, James, 1996-1997 (Box 4)
  - Lumbini project, 1984-1988 (Box 4)
  - M, 1979-2003; 8 folders (Box 4)
  - Madison Zen Center, 1984-1985 (Box 4)
  - Mandel, Charles, 1996 (Box 4)
  - Martin, Rafe (Jataka Tales), 1992-1999; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Mc, 1981-1988; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - McNally, James, 1996-2000 (Box 4)
  - Media and Periodicals, 1973-1980 (Box 4)
  - Mellor, Gary, 1993-1994 (Box 4)
  - Mexico, 1987-1995 (Box 4)
  - Mountain Cloud Zen Center, 1985-1986 (Box 4)
  - Moyers, Scott, 1993-1996 (Box 4)
  - N, 1981-2001; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Nakashima, George, 1975-1978 (Box 4)
  - Netherlands and territories including Antilles, 1970-1984 (Box 4)
  - New York Times, 1965-1979 (Box 4)
  - New Zealand, 1970-1973 (Box 4)
  - Nigeria, 1985 (Box 15)
  - Norway, 1970-1977 (Box 4)
  - O, 1979-2000; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Other Centers, 1979-1994 (Box 5)
  - P, 1980-1995; 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Packer, Toni, 1992-2002 (Box 5)
  - Panama, 1975 (Box 5)
  - Parabola magazine, 1985 (Box 5)
  - Paragon House, 1989-1990 (Box 5)
  - Parker, Frankie, 1996 (Box 5)
  - Petry, Vondell, 1978-1997 (Box 5)
  - Pleasant Valley Ranch, 1993-1996 (Box 5)
  - Poland, 1974-1988; 5 folders (Box 5)
  - Poland, 1977-1994 (Box 15)
  - Prisoners, 1974-1983 (Box 5)
  - Providence Zen Center Ven. Seung Sahn Seun, 1976-1985 (Box 5)
  - Puerto Rico, 1975 (Box 5)
  - Pulleyn, Chris, 1966-1995 (Box 5)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes materials related to writing a biography about Philip Kapleau, including correspondence from Polly Young-Eisendrath, articles, and interviews.
  - Q, 1985-1997 (Box 5)
  - R, 1980-2002; 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Ramirez, Juan, 1975-1983 (Box 5)
  - Rider and Co., 1983 (Box 5)
  - Robert Mitchell's Book on Buddha, 1986-1987 (Box 5)
  - Roberts, Tom, 1978-2002; 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Robicheck, Jim, 1991-1998 (Box 5)
  - Rochester Zen Center, 1977-1996 (Box 5)
  - Rockefeller, Stephen, 1975-1988 (Box 5)
  - Rolodex, 1986-1987, undated (Box 18)
  - Romania, 1979-1983 (Box 5)
  - Rose, James (Leon Shipper), 1967-1983 (Box 5)
  - Rowe, Stephen, 1993 (Box 5)
  - S, 1974-1995; 3 folders (Box 5)
  - S, 1981-2002; 4 folders (Box 6)
  - Sandberg, Ruth, 1969-1997 (Box 6)
  - Sangharakshita and F.W.B.O., 1973-1994 (Box 6)
  - Satcher, David and Sonya, 1993-2003 (Box 6)
  - Schmookler, Andrew Bard, 1988-1998 (Box 6)
  - Schremser, Ethel, 1973-1979 (Box 6)
  - Scotland, undated (Box 6)
  - Sheldon, Jon, 1990-1997 (Box 6)
  - Shen, C.T., 1981-1984 (Box 6)
  - Singapore, 1989 (Box 6)
  - Shambhala Publications, 1999-2000 (Box 6)
  - Shortz, Alan, 1985 (Box 6)
  - Spain, 1971-1985 (Box 6)
  - Spain (Mallorca), 1978-1984 (Box 6)
  - Special letters to Kapleau, 1985-1998 (Box 6)
  - South Africa, 1979-1990; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Sri Lanka, 1971-1973 (Box 6)
  - Stephens, Helen, 1977-1979 (Box 6)
  - Sung, Dr (Korean Leader), 1993 (Box 6)
  - Suzuki, Daisetz T., 1957 (Box 15)
  - Sweden, 1972-1994 (Box 6)
  - Switzerland, 1971-1988 (Box 6)
  - T, 1986-2002; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Taiwan, visit to, 1982-1995; 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Tangen Harada Roshi, 1970-1989 (Box 6)
  - re: Tendzin, Osel, Homosexuality and Buddhism, 1989-1991 (Box 6)
  - The Three Pillars of Zen Reissue 89/99, 1971-1999 (Box 6)
  - Toronto Zen Centre, 1984-1996 (Box 6)
  - U, 1991-2001 (Box 6)
  - V, 1988-1995 (Box 6)
  - Vermont Zen Center, 1986-2000 (Box 6)
  - W, 1982-2004; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Wilcove, Marcy, 1974-1998 (Box 6)
  - Y, 1981-1997 (Box 6)
  - Yamada, Kyozo, 1954 (Box 6)
  - Yasutani, Ryoko (Hakuun), 1957 (Box 6)
  - Young-Eisendrath, Polly, 1966-2002 (Box 7)
  - Yugoslavia, 1988-1994 (Box 7)
  - Z, 1996-1998 (Box 7)
  - Zen Center of Los Angeles, Taizan Maezumi Roshi, 1973-1984 (Box 7)
  - Zen Center San Francisco, Richard Baker Roshi, 1968-1986 (Box 7)
  - Zen Hospice, 1991-1995 (Box 7)
  - Zen Meditation Center, Hollywood, Florida, 1992-1996 (Box 7)
  - The Zen of Living and Dying (formerly "The Wheel of Life and Death"), 1994-1998 (Box 7)
  - Zen Merging of East and West Germany, 2002 (Box 7)
  - Zen Studies Society, Dai Bosatsu Zendo, Eido Tai Shimano Roshi, 1972-1986 (Box 7)
- Subject Files, 1952-2004 and undated; 2
  - 80th Birthday Events, 1965-1992 (Box 7)
  - A, 1967-1992 (Box 7)
  - Abortion, Euthanasia, 1963-1978 (Box 7)
  - Abuses of Power and the Precepts by Kapleau, 1984 (Box 7)
  - Affiliate Centers, 1984-1985 (Box 7)
  - Agriculture, Climates, Earthquakes, 1976-1980 (Box 15)
  - Akegarasu, Haya, 1968-1975 (Box 7)
  - Aikido, Tai Chi-Chuan, Gurdjieff, Subud, etc, 1967-1978 (Box 7)
  - Alexander Technique, 1979-1982 (Box 7)
  - American Anti-Vivisection Society, 1991 (Box 7)
  - Animals, 1967-2000 (Box 7)
  - Animals and Buddhism: Source Materials, 1960-1984, undated; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Animals and Buddhism: Source Materials, 1970-1983 (Box 15)
  - Animal Experimentation, 1980-1985, undated (Box 7)
  - Animal Images, 1982-1983, undated (Box 7)
  - Animals Newsletters, 1985 (Box 7)
  - Animal Research, 1990-1997 (Box 7)
  - Animal Slaughter, 1984-1985 (Box 7)
  - Animal Welfare, 1978-1986; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Art Dealers, Figures, 1974-1980 (Box 7)
  - Articles about the Center and Its Members, 1965-1980 (Box 7)
  - Articles by Philip Kapleau, 1960-1994; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Artwork, 1987 (Box 7)
  - Bassui, Yaeko Iwasaki, "The Three Pillars of Zen" Photographs, 1976 (Box 7)
  - Beekeeping, 1970-1972 (Box 7)
  - Biondi, Joann articles, 1987-1994 (Box 7)
  - Book Inserts for "Zen Dawn"and "To Cherish All Life", Undated (Box 7)
  - Buddha and Mao by Dick Ringler, 1981 (Box 7)
  - Buddha Figures Photographs, 1968, undated (Box 7)
  - Buddha Image, 1972-1981, undated (Box 7)
  - Buddha Mexican, 1978-1979; 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Buddhism, 1965-2000, undated; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Buddhism, 1974 (Box 15)
  - Buddhism in the West Chapter, Undated (Box 7)
  - Buddhism Miscellaneous Notes and Articles, 1952-1985 (Box 7)
  - Buddhism Miscellaneous Notes and Articles, 1956-1994; 4 folders (Box 8)
  - Buddhist Centers, 1993-1996, undated (Box 8)
  - Buddhist Economics, 1975-1976, undated (Box 8)
  - Buddhist Peace Fellowship, 1990-1991 (Box 8)
  - Buddhist, what it means to be a, 1971-1974 (Box 8)
  - Budget, Receipts, Expenses, 1994-2002 (Box 8)
  - Berry, Lynn interview, 1991-1993 (Box 8)
  - Buddhist Stories for Children, Undated (Box 8)
  - C, 1973-1992; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Calendar, 1995 (Box 8)
  - Ceremonies, 1973-1992 (Box 8)
  - Ceremony of Confession and Repentance, 1972 (Box 8)
  - Ceremony of the Release of the Animals, 1973 (Box 8)
  - The Climate of the Monastic Prayer, 1964 (Box 8)
  - Chants, 1972-1982 (Box 8)
  - Chants, translations, 1969-1989, undated; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - To Cherish all Life, Reviews, 1981-1995, undated (Box 8)
  - China article and slide show information, 1981-1982, undated (Box 8)
  - China Literature, 1974-1984 (Box 8)
  - China Pilgrimage Article, 1982 (Box 8)
  - China Pilgrimage Article Notes, 1959-1982, undated (Box 8)
  - China Pilgrimage Article with PK's Epilogue, 1981-1983, undated (Box 8)
  - China Travel, 1984-1985 (Box 8)
  - China Trip, 1978-1981; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Chinmoy, Sri, 1988-1998 (Box 15)
  - Cookbook, Roshi's notes for introduction, 1984-1985 (Box 8)
  - Conference of Western Buddhist Meditation Teachers, 1993 (Box 8)
  - Consciousness, Pain, Sex and Time, 1995, undated (Box 8)
  - Costa Rica, 1979-1983 (Box 8)
  - Creationism, Church and State Separation, 1966-1982 (Box 8)
  - The Cremation of Sam McGee by Robert Service, 1958 (Box 8)
  - Crime and Violence, Punishment, Prison, 1966-1979 (Box 8)
  - Czechoslovakia, 1979 (Box 8)
  - D, 1972-1993, undated (Box 8)
  - Daido Loori Mt. Tremper, undated (Box 8)
  - Daisan, Guidelines for, undated (Box 8)
  - Dalai Lama, 1989-1993 (Box 8)
  - Dalai Lama and the Jews, 1990 (Box 8)
  - Death, 1960-1993 (Box 8)
  - Death, 1967-1988; 8 folders (Box 9)
  - Death, grief and bereavement, 1965-1987 (Box 9)
  - Death, hospice, 1972-1986 (Box 9)
  - Death, karma, 1974-1987 (Box 9)
  - Death, living wills, 1974-1987 (Box 9)
  - Articles on Death and Dying Since the Publication of the Wheel of Life and Death, 1968-1991; 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Disciples of Philip Kapleau, 1962-1995 (Box 9)
  - Dogen: His Writings and Materials About him, 1959-1973, undated (Box 9)
  - Drugs, Psychedelics, Pot etc., 1963-1990 (Box 9)
  - Dying, 1958-1988; 3 folders (Box 9)
  - Dying, euthanasia, 1962-1987 (Box 9)
  - Ecology and Economy, Environment, 1969-1993, undated (Box 9)
  - Ecumenical Conference, Peace Prayer, Mexico, 1989 June 30 (Box 9)
  - Education of a Japanese Banker Article, 1978 (Box 9)
  - Elder, John "Japan and US Embassy", 1992 (Box 9)
  - Ethics and Morality, 1984-1991 (Box 9)
  - Faith and Belief, 1969-1992 (Box 9)
  - Faith in Mind, 1972-1979 (Box 9)
  - Florida House, 1989-1997 (Box 15)
  - Flowers Poem, Undated (Box 9)
  - Food Macrobiotics, 1966-1972 (Box 10)
  - Founders Day Talk, 1975 August (Box 10)
  - Govinda, Lama, 1964-1979 (Box 10)
  - The Hands by D.T. Suzuki, 1952 (Box 10)
  - Harada-Roshi, 1962-1971 (Box 10)
  - Healing, Therapies, Medical, 1970-1984 (Box 10)
  - Health, 1967-2002; 7 folders (Box 10)
  - Health, cancer, 1963-1978; 4 folders (Box 10)
  - Health, Diet, 1972-1993 (Box 10)
  - Health, Parkinson's, 1981-2002; 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Health Parkinson's Hope Newsletter, 1991-1995 (Box 10)
  - Health Prostate, 1981-1991 (Box 10)
  - Health Sleep, 1988-1994 (Box 10)
  - Heaven on Earth by Roger S Gottlieb, 1991 (Box 10)
  - The Holographic Model by Renee Weber, 1988 (Box 10)
  - Is Humanity Suicidal by E. O. Wilson, 1993 (Box 10)
  - Hunger, 1981-1983 (Box 10)
  - Illiteracy, 1984-1986 (Box 10)
  - India "Art and the Life of India", 1985 (Box 10)
  - Indians (Native), 1981 (Box 10)
  - Indonesia, 1967-1983 (Box 10)
  - Insight Meditation Practice Manual, 1977 (Box 10)
  - International Networks for Religion of Animals, 1989 (Box 10)
  - Islam, 1982 (Box 10)
  - Japan and China, articles about, 1986-1992 (Box 10)
  - Japan, articles about, 1963-1993 (Box 10)
  - Japan clippings, 1995 (Box 10)
  - Japanese Gravestones, 1966 June (Box 10)
  - Judaism, 1980-1985 (Box 10)
  - Jukai, 1964-1996 (Box 11)
  - Kapleau Obituaries, 2004 (Box 15)
  - Karma, 1959-1986 (Box 11)
  - Kensho experiences not under Kapleau, 1963-1969 (Box 11)
  - Kisa Gotami Mustard Seed Story, 1957 (Box 11)
  - Koan Number 47:Tosotsu's Three Barriers, undated (Box 11)
  - Koans, 1952-1972, undated (Box 11)
  - Language, 1948-1986 (Box 11)
  - Lectures on Hakuin Zenji's Chant in Praise of Zazen draft by Yamada Mumon and translated by Kenneth Craft, 1975 (Box 11)
  - Living Will of Philip Kapleau, 1988-1997 (Box 11)
  - M, 1974-1987 (Box 11)
  - Man's Justice and God's Justice" by Kapleau, 1993-1994 (Box 11)
  - Meditation and Everyone manuscript draft by Subagh Singh Khalsa, 1993 (Box 11)
  - Meditations and Death, 1987-1990 (Box 11)
  - Meditations, Zen and Other Traditions, 1963-1987 (Box 11)
  - Miami Kannon, 1994 (Box 11)
  - Midori Gallery, Sachi, 1995 (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous, 1954-1999; 4 folders (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous, 1965-1996; 4 folders (Box 11)
  - Monasticism, Ordination, Celibacy and The Lay Order, 1959-1986; 3 folders (Box 11)
  - Morita Therapy, 1958-1971 (Box 11)
  - Muktananda/Baker, Coevolution journal, 1983 (Box 11)
  - Music, Records, Tapes, 1969-1973 (Box 11)
  - Mystical Experiences of the Labor Camps by Mihajlo Mihajlov, 1977-1983 (Box 11)
  - Mysticism, 1967 (Box 11)
  - N, 1984-1990 (Box 11)
  - National Health Federation, 1956-1975 (Box 11)
  - Newsletters of Various Zen Centers, 1984-1996; 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Nonviolence, 1985-1986 (Box 11)
  - Non-violence in Theravada Buddhism draft by Don Swearer, 1986 (Box 11)
  - Norway, 1988-1990 (Box 11)
  - Nuclear, 1977-1986 (Box 11)
  - Old Age, 1979-1980 (Box 12)
  - Omega "Eldering", 1976-1994 (Box 12)
  - Omega Institute, 1962-1991 (Box 12)
  - Organ Donation, 1984-1987 (Box 12)
  - Oversize Print Materials, 1983-1990, undated (Oversize-folder 1)
    New Mexican Sesshin Facility Plan; Thich Nhat Hanh, Gary Snyder, and Philip Kapleau Event in New York Poster; Taller de Zen Event in Mexico.
  - Out-of-town workshops and sesshins, 1966-1983 (Box 12)
  - Oxherding Verses Various Translations, 1963 (Box 12)
  - P, 1982-1984 (Box 12)
  - Packer, Toni Split from Rochester Zen Center, 1981 (Box 12)
  - Packer, Toni Springwater Center, 1995 (Box 12)
  - Packing List for Roshi, 1979-1985 (Box 15)
  - Pain, 1973-1991 (Box 12)
  - Paloma (P.K.'s dog), 1987 (Box 15)
  - Pamphlets, Journals, and Ephemera, 1958-1996; 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Paranormal Phenomena, M. Crichton's Reply to Critics Thereof, Undated (Box 12)
  - Patriarchs, First Five, 1974 (Box 12)
  - Peace March, 1982 (Box 12)
  - Persian Gulf Crisis, F.O.R. Statement, 1990 (Box 12)
  - Physics, 1983 March (Box 12)
  - PK Interview with Ken Kraft Yoga Journal, 1991 (Box 12)
  - Plant Sensitivity, 1971-1983 (Box 12)
  - Poland, 1983 (Box 12)
  - The Politics of Prajna by Nelson Foster, Undated (Box 15)
  - Population and Hunger, 1976-1986 (Box 12)
  - Posture and Breathing, 1972-1980 (Box 12)
  - Pseudo-Religions and Cults, EST, Arica, Moon Scientology, 1967-1991 (Box 12)
  - Psychology, 1968-1993 (Box 12)
  - Psychology, Psychiatry, Mental Health, Brain Waves, 1963-1983; 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Pyramids, 1972-1978 (Box 12)
  - Questions and Answers about Zazen, undated (Box 12)
  - Rebirth, 1972-1987 (Box 12)
  - Rebirth near death experiences, 1956-1986 (Box 12)
  - Religion, 1957-1992; 5 folders (Box 12)
  - Rochester Zen Center, 1976-1999; 3 folders (Box 12)
  - Rochester Zen Center 20th Anniversary, 1983-1986 (Box 13)
  - Rochester Zen Center 30th Anniversary, 1996-2002 (Box 13)
  - Rockefeller, Steven, 1981-1994 (Box 13)
  - Right to Die Society, undated (Box 13)
  - Rinzai Roku, 1991 (Box 13)
  - Rituals, Ceremonies, Celebrations, 1965-1976 (Box 13)
  - Roshi Kapleau's Formal Students, 1990 (Box 13)
  - Roshi's Japanese Books, 1979 (Box 13)
  - Sandberg, Ruth Talks, 1974-1986 (Box 13)
  - Science (astronomy, archeology, etc), 1956-1984 (Box 13)
  - Sekida, Katsuki, 1967-1970; 2 folders (Box 13)
  - 11-Sep-01, 2001 (Box 13)
  - Dr Shen Monastery, 1991 (Box 13)
  - Social Security and Medicare, 1960-1994 (Box 13)
  - Soka Gakkai and Toynbee article, 1984 (Box 15)
  - Sonam Remedies, 1991-1992 (Box 13)
  - Staff Guidelines South Florida Center, Undated (Box 13)
  - Stupas, 1983-1985 (Box 13)
  - Suffering in Religions of the World by John Bowker, 1970 (Box 13)
  - Suicide, 1951-1988 (Box 13)
  - Sunshine Magazine Profile of Kapleau by Joann Biondi, 1994 (Box 13)
  - Suzuki D. T., 1950-1960 (Box 13)
  - Symbols, 1963-1978 (Box 13)
  - Teishos, 1974-1994 (Box 13)
  - Teishos non-koan, 1968-1993 (Box 13)
  - Thich Nhat Hanh, Gary Snyder, and Philip Kapleau Event in New York, 1983 (Box 13)
  - Thich Nhat Hanh, Disciplines of His Order, Undated (Box 15)
  - Thought Understanding in Wittgenstein and Zen draft by John Canfield, 1974 (Box 13)
  - Three Pillars Audio Project, 1995 (Box 13)
  - Three Pillars of Zen, materials and translations for, 1957, undated (Box 13)
  - Three Pillars of Zen Reviews, 1965-1996 (Box 13)
  - Transcendental Meditation an expose, 1993 (Box 13)
  - The Tree Sitter and the Sesame Seed by pb hunter, Undated (Box 13)
  - Vegetarianism, 1951-2001; 4 folders (Box 13)
  - Venezuela, 1989 (Box 13)
  - Violence and Religion, 1982 (Box 13)
  - Weddings, 1967-1996 (Box 13)
  - Wheel of Life General, 1988-1993 (Box 13)
  - Wheel of Life and Death omitted material, 1989-1998 (Box 13)
  - Wheel of Life and Death Reviews and Quotations, 1989-1990 (Box 13)
  - Work, 1966-1995 (Box 13)
  - Yoga, 1971-1976 (Box 13)
  - Zen and Buddhism, Masao Abe, 1965-1976 (Box 13)
  - Zen and Business, 1966-1975 (Box 13)
  - Zen and Psychotherapy, 1972-1993; 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Zen: Dawn in the West, French Translation, 1980-1981 (Box 14)
  - Zen Meditation Center, Hollywood, Florida, 1993-1995 (Box 14)
  - Zen: Merging of East and West, 1988 (Box 14)
- Recorded Teishos (Dharma Talks), 1975-2001 and undated; 3